Guide to the War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work Records
1941-1945
RG 99
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(13 boxes)
The records document the effect of war time emergency measures on student religious work on college and university campuses throughout the United States during the years 1942 to 1944. The War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work was established in 1942 to deal with the readjustments made necessary by the impact of World War II on college and university campuses. The Council collected and disseminated information, arranged regional consultative conferences, and worked as an intermediary between the United States military establishment and student religious movements.
War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
The War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work was established in 1942 to deal with the readjustments made necessary by the impact of the Second World War on college and university campuses. The following ten factors were cited in a memorandum calling for readjustment of student Christian movement activities:
1. After February 1, 1943 practically all able-bodied men over 18 in the colleges will be in some form of military training and under military discipline.
2. Free time and vacations will be on a minimum basis.
3. Non-scientific courses for men will be largely eliminated.
4. It is probable that the program of military training may be largely concentrated in a limited number of the larger institutions.
5. Some colleges are considering a lowering of entrance requirements, which would greatly increase the proportion of underclassmen.
6. Increasing numbers of women's units (military, industrial, etc.) will be located on campuses.
7. Leaders in higher education are having little part in determining war-time educational plans.
8. In most larger military units chaplains probably will be provided.
9. Any work done by voluntary agencies within military units on the campus will be by military permission.
10. All of the above factors, plus the growing emphasis upon consolidated financial appeals, creates a serious crisis for the financing of our regular work, locally, regionally and nationally.
The Council initially was composed of members representing The National Commission on University Work of the Council of Church Boards of Education (denominational student Christian work) and the National Intercollegiate Christian Council (YMCA, YWCA, and regional Student Christian Movements). The Student Volunteer Movement was invited to become a member of the War Emergency Council in October, 1943.
The War Emergency Council collected and disseminated information, arranged regional consultative conferences, and worked as an intermediary between the United States military establishment and student religious movements. Negotiations between the War Emergency Council and military officials cleared the way for resident religious agencies on American campuses to be of service to students who were part of the armed services.
To facilitate coordination in dealing with the war-time emergency situation, the Council worked with the National Catholic Welfare Conference and the B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations to form the Inter-Religious Council. The War Emergency Council also worked with the Department of Evangelism of the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America to form the Christian Commission on War Time Campus Missions. The War Emergency Council played a role in "awakening both students and student leaders throughout the country to the necessity and the possibility of an officially appointed Council representing the various organizations as an instrument of clearance in all their cooperative activities."
In September 1944, the purposes, functions, and organization of the War Emergency Council were transferred to the newly formed United Student Christian Council in the U.S.A., constituting its War Emergency Committee.
Scope and Contents
The Minutes of Series I provide an overview of the activities of the War Emergency Council and its interactions with other organizations. The series includes agendas and other materials related to the meetings for which minutes are available.
The Correspondence of Series II includes correspondence of the executive secretaries of the Council, A. Roland Elliott, and his successor, R.H. Edwin Espy, as well as the correspondence of Assistant Secretary Betty Herrold and other individuals associated with the Council. Prominent correspondents include Fern Babcock, Henry Sloane Coffin, Frederick B. Igler, George Johnson of the National Catholic Welfare Conference, Alden Kelley, Clarence Shedd, Abram L. Sachar of the B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations, Henry P. Van Dusen, Gould Wickey, and George Zook of the American Council on Education. There is also correspondence with various representatives of the United States military. Some Council correspondence relating to conferences, surveys, and publications is located in Series III, PROGRAM DOCUMENTATION.
Series III, Program Documentation, contains materials related to the Council's efforts to collect and disseminate information relating to the impact of the war on student religious work. It contains documentation of literature prepared and published, surveys done, conferences arranged, and visits made to campuses. Factual information contained in this series provides insight into conditions on campuses throughout the United States during the Second World War.
The Financial Records of Series IV reflect not only the financial operations of the Council itself, but also the financial needs of local and regional student religious agencies during this time period.
Series V, Related Organizations and Material, contains documentation collected by the War Emergency Council concerning other organizations involved in higher education and/or student religious work during the wartime period. Some of these materials are similar to the PROGRAM DOCUMENTATION of Series III, but, in general, the collected materials of this series are less directly related to the program goals and initiatives of the Council.
Arrangement
I. Minutes, 1942-1944
II.Correspondence, 1942-1945
III. Program Documentation, 1942- 1944
IV. Financial Records, 1942-1945
V. Related Organizations and Material, 1941-1944
College students -- Religious life; Universities and colleges -- Religion; World War, 1939-1945; Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1877-1954; Elliott, Arthur Roland, 1895-; Espy, R. H. Edwin; Grant, Fern Babcock, 1904-; Herrold, Betty; Sachar, Abram Leon, 1899-1993; Shedd, Clarence Prouty, 1887-; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975; Wickey, Gould, 1891-; Zook, George Frederick, 1885-1951; War Emergency Council on Student Christian Work
- Minutes, 1942-1944; Series I
  - Council in process of formation, 1942 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Full Council meetings - Cincinnati, 1943 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Full Council meeting - Wooster, 1943 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Full Council meeting - New York, 1944 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
  - Executive Committee, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Correspondence, 1942-1945; Series II
  - A. Roland Elliott
    - Correspondence, 1942 Jan-1943 Mar (Box 1, Folder 14-22)
    - Correspondence, 1943 Apr-Jul (Box 2, Folder 23-26)
  - R.H. Edwin Espy (Secretary of WEC)
    - Correspondence, 1943 Jun-1945 Mar, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
  - War Emergency Council office files for 1943
    Scope and Contents
    Files of Betty Herrold, Assistant Secretary
    - Adams, Carlyle; Adams, John Maxwell (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Babcock, Fern (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Bader - Braisted (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Bremer - French (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Forsyth - Holmer (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hovey - Kagin (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Kelley, Alden (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Kitchen - Mott (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Norris - Seamans (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Shedd, Clarence (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Thompson - Wickey (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Wiggin - Workman (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - War Emergency Council office files for 1944
    - Adams - Bollinger (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Braisted - Espy (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Fairgraves - Getty (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Giffen - Guthrie (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Howell - Kaplan (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Kelley - Maguire (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Mains - Schiotz (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Shedd - Turnbull (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Van Dusen - Woodward (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Mailing list of campuses and churches (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Form letters and forms (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Program Documentation, 1942- 1944; Series III
  - Memoranda re. relationships with other organizations, 1942-1944, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Consultative Conferences - general, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Consultative Conferences - Pacific Northwest, 1943 May,Dec (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Consultative Conferences - Pacific Southwest, 1943 May
  - Consultative Conferences - Kentucky, Georgia, 1943 Jun (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Consultative Conferences - No. Carolina, Kansas,Tennessee, 1943 Nov
  - Consultative Conferences - New England, 1943 Nov (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Consultative Conferences - Midwest Region, 1944 Jan
  - Consultative Conferences - Southwest, 1944 Feb
  - Consultative Conferences - Colorado, 1944 Mar
  - Consultative Conferences - YMCA-sponsored, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Student work in wartime - general (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Students in uniform - general (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Campuses with military training units (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Survey of campuses with military trainees to locate schools needing aid (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Survey of 25 colleges in Pacific NW area (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - List of 218 campuses with war training (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - List of campus coordinators on campuses with training units (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Educational institutions inspected: War Dept.- Navy Dept. Manpower Commission (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Educational institutions approved: War Dept. - Navy Dept. Manpower Commission (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Women on campuses in wartime (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Military training programs in highereducational institutions (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Military enrollment in instructional programs in colleges and universities. (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Student and college survey - study made by Henry David Gray, Division of Christian Education, Congregational Christian Churches, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Basic data on student religious work for Army-Navy trainees: Amherst College - Louisiana State University (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Basic data on student religious work for Army-Navy trainees: Massachusetts State College - University of Alabama (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Basic data on student religious work for Army-Navy trainees: University of California - University of Oklahoma (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Basic data on student religious work for Army-Navy trainees: University of Pittsburgh - Yale University (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Records of service done by campus Y's to trainees: General (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Records of service done by campus Y's to trainees: Amarillo Junior College - Mississippi State University (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Records of service done by campus Y's to trainees: North Carolina State University - University of Michigan (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Records of service done by campus Y's to trainees: University of Nebraska - Yankston College (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Religious work with trainees in colleges (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: A M College of Texas - Brown University (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: Bucknell University - Cornell University (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: Johns Hopkins University - Ohio State University (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: Pomona College - University of Oregon (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: University of Pittsburgh - University of Wisconsin (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Christian Associations on the campuses: Virginia Polytechnic - Yale University (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Religious organizations on campuses, including Jewish and Catholic, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - "The Work of the College Religious Forces with the Special Training Units" by Benjamin R. Andrews, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Staff campus visitation schedule, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Reports of visitations to campuses with training units, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Speakers to Military Training Units (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Communique: Wartime Information for Student Christian Associations: Issues (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Communique: Wartime Information for Student Christian Associations: Issues, 1943 Feb, Mar, May (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Communique: Wartime Information for Student Christian Associations: Issues, 1943 Jun, Oct, Dec (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Communique: Wartime Information for Student Christian Associations: Issues, 1944 Feb, May (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Communique: Manuscripts and drafts of articles (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Communique: Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Communique: Mailing lists (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Manuscripts considered for publication (Box 10, Folder 103,104)
  - Re. literature and publications (Box 10, Folder 105)
- Financial Records, 1942-1945; Series IV
  - Financial records, 1942 Oct- 1945 Oct, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 106-111)
- Related Organizations and Material, 1941-1944; Series V
  An alphabetical listing of related organizations is followed by five folders of miscellaneous published material.
  - American Council on Education: Higher Education and National Defense - bulletin, 1943 Jan -1944 Jun (Box 11, Folder 112-114)
  - Catholic Association for International Peace, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Christian Commission on Wartime Campus Ministries, 1943 Oct-1944 Oct (Box 11, Folder 116-118)
  - Commission to Study the Organization of Peace, 1941-1943 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Congregational Christian Study of World Organization, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Guardians of America, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Informal Conference on Church Relations with Post War Europe, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Inter-Religious Council: Formation Meeting, 1942 Dec 10 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Inter-Religious Council: Correspondence re. appointments to Advisory Committee, 1942 Dec-1943 Mar (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Inter-Religious Council: News release, Meeting, 1943 Jan 15; 1943 Feb 17 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Inter-Religious Council: Meetings, 1943 Mar 22; 1943 May 14 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Inter-Religious Council: Survey of Religious Organizations on Campus, 1942-1943 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Methodist Church, Wesley Foundations (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - National Intercollegiate Christian Council: War Emergency Committee, 1942 Nov-Dec (Box 11, Folder 129)
  - National Intercollegiate Christian Council: The Intercollegian, 1943 Apr-Dec (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - Pacific School of Religion - Training for Post-War Rehabilitation Abroad, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., Board of Christian Education, 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Public Affairs Committee, Inc., 1944 (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Student Planning Conference on the World Mission of the Church, Continuation Committee, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - U.S.O. - program material, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - United States Navy - Navy V-12 Bulletin No. 12 "Manual for the Operation of a Navy V-12 Unit", 1943 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - United States Office of Education, Federal Security Agency: Education for Victory, 1943 May-Aug (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - United States Office of Education, Federal Security Agency: Education for Victory, 1943 Sep-Dec (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - United States Office of Education, Federal Security Agency: Education for Victory, 1944 Jan-Mar (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - United States Office of Education, Federal Security Agency: Education for Victory, 1944 Apr-Jul (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - United States War Department, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - University Commission of the Council of Church Boards of Education, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - World Council of Churches, Provisional Committee, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - World's Student Christian Federation, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - YMCA - misc. program material, 1942-1944 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - YMCA, National Council, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - YMCA, Southern Area Council, Committee to Disseminate Information on the World of the Future, 1941-1943 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - YMCA, student committees, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 146)
  - YWCA, National Student Council Wartime Expansion Program Committee, 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Local and regional YMCA and SCM publications, 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Miscellaneous writings and speeches re. war and reconstruction, 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - Information re. motion pictures (program material), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1942 Nov-1944 (Box 13, Folder 150,151)